<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>malaria | Nick Brazeau</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/tags/malaria/</link><atom:link href="https://nicholasbrazeau.com/tags/malaria/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>malaria</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 Nicholas Brazeau</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/img/headers/tree.jpg</url><title>malaria</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/tags/malaria/</link></image><item><title>Antimalarial Resistance in Ethiopia</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/ephiamr/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/ephiamr/</guid><description>&lt;p>Using samples collected as part of antimalarial drug efficacy studies across Ethiopia over multiple years, we demonstrated that &lt;em>P. falciparum&lt;/em> parasites have evidence of persistence through space and time, despite differing profiles of antimalarial resistance. A main focus of this project was capacity building and increased molecular surveillance capacity at the Ethiopian Public Health Institute and was the first project of a lasting collaboration between the EPHI and UNC. This project was published in the American Journal of Tropical Medicine &amp;amp; Hygeine&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Assefa A, Mohammed H, Seme H, Tsadik AG, Parr JB, Keeler C, Hathaway NJ, Meshnick SR, Bailey JA, Kassa M, Juliano JJ, Woyessa A. Pooled Deep Sequencing of Drug Resistance Loci from Plasmodium falciparum Parasites across Ethiopia. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2019 Nov;101(5):1139-1143. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.19-0142. PMID: 31516103; PMCID: PMC6838589.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>`DISCent`: Spatial Inbreeding Estimation</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/discent/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/discent/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a simple package with a single function that runs a simple isolation by distance and identity by descent model for producing deme inbreeding spatial coefficients (DISCs). By theory, genetic relatnedness is strictly limited to measure of identity by descent. For a full mathematical overview of the simple model, please see the supplements from Brazeau et al. 2022 in in preperation&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Briefly, in the early 1970s, Malécot described a relationship between genetic relatedness and physical distance under the premise that pairs that are far apart are less likely to mate: isolation by distance. Capitalizing on this framework by using measures of identity by descent (IBD), we produce a deme inbreeding spatial coefficient (DISC) for point process data in continuous space. Essentially, this measure estimates the amount of &amp;ldquo;inbreeding&amp;rdquo; or within deme relatedness under the assumption that relatedness between two locations in space can be measured from the average pairwise IBD between those two locations conditional on the physical distance that separates them. Further, we assume that geographic distance is scaled by a migration rate, which is a global parameter among all spatial locations (i.e. the migration rate is assumed to be constant through space). As a result, the model produces a DISC for each spatial location considered (user defined) and an overall migration rate parameter (m). Parameter optimization is achieved with a &amp;ldquo;vanilla&amp;rdquo; gradient descent algorithm. Given that &amp;ldquo;vanilla&amp;rdquo; gradient descent is used, we recommend running numerous models from a wide of array of start parameters to ensure that your final results are the global maximum and not a local maximum (i.e. a false peak).&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Nicholas F Brazeau, &lt;em>in preparation&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Household Prevalence of Plasmodium falciparum, Plasmodium vivax, and Plasmodium ovale in the Democratic Republic of the Congo, 2013-2014</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/mitchell-household-2021/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/mitchell-household-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Vivax in the DRC</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/drcpv/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/drcpv/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> has long been assumed to be essentially extinct in Sub-Saharan Africa. In this manuscript, we combine techniques from causal inference epidemiolgy, spatial epidemiology, and bioinformatics to describes who is being infected by &lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> in the DRC, where infections are occurring, and where the infections potentially originated. Overall, we suggest that &lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> is persisting in the DRC rather than expanding or thriving. This project was published as Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2021 in Nature Communications&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Mitchell CL, Morgan AP, Deutsch-Feldman M, Watson OJ, Thwai KL, Gelabert P, van Dorp L, Keeler CY, Waltmann A, Emch M, Gartner V, Redelings B, Wray GA, Mwandagalirwa MK, Tshefu AK, Likwela JL, Edwards JK, Verity R, Parr JB, Meshnick SR, Juliano JJ. The epidemiology of Plasmodium vivax among adults in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Nat Commun. 2021 Jul 7;12(1):4169. doi: 10.1038/s41467-021-24216-3. PMID: 34234124; PMCID: PMC8263614.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>The epidemiology of Plasmodium vivax among adults in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-epidemiology-2021/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-epidemiology-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Burden of Malaria in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/deutsch-feldman-burden-2021/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/deutsch-feldman-burden-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Under the Radar: Epidemiology of Plasmodium ovale in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/mitchell-under-2021/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/mitchell-under-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Selection of Cytochrome b Mutants Is Rare among Plasmodium falciparum Patients Failing Treatment with Atovaquone-Proguanil in Cambodia</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/lin-selection-2021/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/lin-selection-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Spatial Patterns of Falciparum Malaria Genetic Relatedness Driven by Human Movement in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 08:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Remote presentation at the annual American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene conference. Presented early work on the Deme Inbreeding Spatial Coefficient framework and the &lt;code>DISCent&lt;/code> R-package. This project is currently in preparation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Potential impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on HIV, tuberculosis, and malaria in low-income and middle-income countries: a modelling study</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/hogan-potential-2020/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/hogan-potential-2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Spatial and epidemiological drivers of Plasmodium falciparum malaria among adults in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/deutsch-feldman-spatial-2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/deutsch-feldman-spatial-2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>`polySimIBD`: A Simple Malaria Genetic Model</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/polysimibd/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/polysimibd/</guid><description>&lt;p>The goal of polySimIBD is to perform forwards in-time simulation of malaria population genetics. The model uses a discrete-time, discrete-loci structured Wright Fisher approximation to account for (simplified) malaria transmission dynamics and can be parameterized across demes to include a spatial component.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The model was originally used in Verity &amp;amp; Aydemir &amp;amp; Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020 in Nature Communications&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> to assess the bias in our identity by descent calculation.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Verity R, Aydemir O, Brazeau NF, Watson OJ, Hathaway NJ, Mwandagalirwa MK, Marsh PW, Thwai K, Fulton T, Denton M, Morgan AP, Parr JB, Tumwebaze PK, Conrad M, Rosenthal PJ, Ishengoma DS, Ngondi J, Gutman J, Mulenga M, Norris DE, Moss WJ, Mensah BA, Myers-Hansen JL, Ghansah A, Tshefu AK, Ghani AC, Meshnick SR, Bailey JA, Juliano JJ. The impact of antimalarial resistance on the genetic structure of Plasmodium falciparum in the DRC. Nat Commun. 2020 Apr 30;11(1):2107. doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-15779-8. PMID: 32355199; PMCID: PMC7192906.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Antimalarial Resistance in the DRC</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/veritydrc/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/veritydrc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Using a massively parallel amplicon sequencing barcode approach, we used genomic analyses to demonstrate that the DRC appears to be a &amp;ldquo;mixing pot&amp;rdquo; for &lt;em>P. falciparum&lt;/em> infections across Sub-Saharan Africa. In addition, we identified strong signals of selection to antimalarial drugs in the DRC that likely have driven gene flow patterns across the country. Alongside analytic support, I lead the analyses on detecting selection using adapted extended haplotype heterozygosity approaches. In addition, I led the bioinformatic analysis identifying the variants for the aforementioned barcode used in the study. This barcode has been used extensively by our research group, as well as several domestic and international groups (initial publication: Verity/Aydemir/Brazeau et al. 2020, Nat Comms).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tanzania-Zanzibar Transmission</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/tzzb_ibd/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/tzzb_ibd/</guid><description>&lt;p>Significant achievements have been made in Zanzibar in reducing the burden of malaria. However, the region has not been able to achieve malaria elimination. We find that despite existing excellent control efforts, there is ample evidence for gene flow and importation between Zanzibar and mainland Tanzania. This study highlights the challenges for elimination campaigns in addressing sink-source dynamics and the difficulties of blocking genetic corridors, which in theory should lead to a lack of diversity and ecological collapse of the malaria parasite in regions undergoing elimination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project was published as Morgan &amp;amp; Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020 in the Malaria Journal&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Morgan AP, Brazeau NF, Ngasala B, Mhamilawa LE, Denton M, Msellem M, Morris U, Filer DL, Aydemir O, Bailey JA, Parr JB, Mårtensson A, Bjorkman A, Juliano JJ. Falciparum malaria from coastal Tanzania and Zanzibar remains highly connected despite effective control efforts on the archipelago. Malar J. 2020 Jan 28;19(1):47. doi: 10.1186/s12936-020-3137-8. PMID: 31992305; PMCID: PMC6988337.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>The impact of antimalarial resistance on the genetic structure of Plasmodium falciparum in the DRC</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/verity-impact-2020/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/verity-impact-2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Falciparum malaria from coastal Tanzania and Zanzibar remains highly connected despite effective control efforts on the archipelago</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/morgan-falciparum-2020/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/morgan-falciparum-2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Epidemiology of Asymptomatic P. vivax Among Adults in the Democratic Republic of the Congoo</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 08:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Presentation of the first aim of my PhD dissertation, which focused on the epidemiology of &lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> in the Democratic Republic of the Congo, at the annual American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene conference. This work is now published in Nature Communications&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1">&lt;sup>1&lt;/sup>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
&lt;hr />
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn1">&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Mitchell CL, Morgan AP, Deutsch-Feldman M, Watson OJ, Thwai KL, Gelabert P, van Dorp L, Keeler CY, Waltmann A, Emch M, Gartner V, Redelings B, Wray GA, Mwandagalirwa MK, Tshefu AK, Likwela JL, Edwards JK, Verity R, Parr JB, Meshnick SR, Juliano JJ. The epidemiology of Plasmodium vivax among adults in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Nat Commun. 2021 Jul 7;12(1):4169. doi: 10.1038/s41467-021-24216-3. PMID: 34234124; PMCID: PMC8263614.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back">↩︎&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Pooled Deep Sequencing of Drug Resistance Loci from Plasmodium falciparum Parasites across Ethiopia</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-pooled-2019/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-pooled-2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Prevalence of Molecular Markers of Antimalarial Drug Resistance across Altitudinal Transmission Zones in Highland Western Uganda</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/boyce-prevalence-2019/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/boyce-prevalence-2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The changing landscape of Plasmodium falciparum drug resistance in the Democratic Republic of Congo</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/deutsch-feldman-changing-2019/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/deutsch-feldman-changing-2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Plasmodium vivax chloroquine resistance links to pvcrt transcription in a genetic cross</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/sa-plasmodium-2019/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/sa-plasmodium-2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Plasmodium vivax Infections in Duffy-Negative Individuals in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-plasmodium-2018/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-plasmodium-2018/</guid><description/></item><item><title>polyIBD: Inferring Identity by Descent in Complex, Polyclonal Infections</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 08:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Presentation at the annual Genomic Epidemiology of Malaria conference presenting early work on &lt;code>polyIBD&lt;/code> a hidden Markov model for inferring identity by descent in polyclonal infections using a Bayesian framework. This project is currently in preparation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Whole Genome Analysis of Polyclonal Plasmodium vivax Relapses in Cambodia</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/pvrelapse-astmh/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 08:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/pvrelapse-astmh/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Oral presentation at the annual American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene conference analyzing the genomics of &lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> relapses from Cambodia.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Partner-Drug Resistance and Population Substructuring of Artemisinin-Resistant Plasmodium falciparum in Cambodia</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/parobek-partner-drug-2017/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/parobek-partner-drug-2017/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Longitudinal Pooled Deep Sequencing of the Plasmodium vivax K12 Kelch Gene in Cambodia Reveals a Lack of Selection by Artemisinin</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-longitudinal-2016/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-longitudinal-2016/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Exclusive Breastfeeding and Clinical Malaria Risk in 6-Month-Old Infants: A Cross-Sectional Study from Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of the Congo</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-exclusive-2016/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/publication/brazeau-exclusive-2016/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>