<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>r | Nick Brazeau</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/categories/r/</link><atom:link href="https://nicholasbrazeau.com/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>r</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Nicholas Brazeau</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/img/headers/tree.jpg</url><title>r</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/categories/r/</link></image><item><title>AMR in the Hospital</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/sepidapto/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/sepidapto/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this case study of a patient with &lt;em>Staphylococcus epidermidis&lt;/em> bacteremia receiving prolonged antibiotics that developed Daptomycin resistance, we used whole genome sequencing and bioinformatic analyses to identify a novel mutation. This project demonstrated the utility in using genomic analysis for the identification and survelliance of putative antimicrobial resistant mutations. This project was published as Brazeau &amp;amp; Levinson &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020 in Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Levinson KJ, Schranz A, Moser KA, Hollis I, Iyer P, Chien C, Bowen A, van Duin D, Lachiewicz A, Andermann T, Jones M, Miller M, Juliano JJ, Bartelt LA. Loss of daptomycin susceptibility in clinical Staphylococcus epidermidis infection coincided with variants in WalK. Evol Med Public Health. 2020 Sep 7;2020(1):219-224. doi: 10.1093/emph/eoaa031. PMID: 33214904; PMCID: PMC7658547.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Antimalarial Resistance in Ethiopia</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/ephiamr/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/ephiamr/</guid><description>&lt;p>Using samples collected as part of antimalarial drug efficacy studies across Ethiopia over multiple years, we demonstrated that &lt;em>P. falciparum&lt;/em> parasites have evidence of persistence through space and time, despite differing profiles of antimalarial resistance. A main focus of this project was capacity building and increased molecular surveillance capacity at the Ethiopian Public Health Institute and was the first project of a lasting collaboration between the EPHI and UNC. This project was published in the American Journal of Tropical Medicine &amp;amp; Hygeine&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Assefa A, Mohammed H, Seme H, Tsadik AG, Parr JB, Keeler C, Hathaway NJ, Meshnick SR, Bailey JA, Kassa M, Juliano JJ, Woyessa A. Pooled Deep Sequencing of Drug Resistance Loci from Plasmodium falciparum Parasites across Ethiopia. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2019 Nov;101(5):1139-1143. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.19-0142. PMID: 31516103; PMCID: PMC6838589.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>IFR Re-estimation</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/reestimateifr/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/reestimateifr/</guid><description>&lt;p>For a summary of these early re-estimates of the COVID-19 first wave infection fatality ratio estimates accounting for seroreversion, please see the associated &lt;a href="https://www.imperial.ac.uk/news/207273/covid19-deaths-infection-fatality-ratio-says/">press release&lt;/a> that accompanied Report 34&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Verity R, Jenks S, Fu H, Whittaker C, Winskill P, Dorigatti I, Walker PGT, Riley S, Schnekenberg RP, Hoeltgebaum H, Mellan TA, Mishra S, Unwin HJT, Watson OJ, Cucunubá ZM, Baguelin M, Whittles L, Bhatt S, Ghani AC, Ferguson NM, Okell LC.. Report 34 - COVID-19 Infection Fatality Ratio Estimates from Seroprevalence. October 2020. &lt;a href="https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-34-ifr">https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-34-ifr&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>`DISCent`: Spatial Inbreeding Estimation</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/discent/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/discent/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a simple package with a single function that runs a simple isolation by distance and identity by descent model for producing deme inbreeding spatial coefficients (DISCs). By theory, genetic relatnedness is strictly limited to measure of identity by descent. For a full mathematical overview of the simple model, please see the supplements from Brazeau et al. 2022 in in preperation&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Briefly, in the early 1970s, Malécot described a relationship between genetic relatedness and physical distance under the premise that pairs that are far apart are less likely to mate: isolation by distance. Capitalizing on this framework by using measures of identity by descent (IBD), we produce a deme inbreeding spatial coefficient (DISC) for point process data in continuous space. Essentially, this measure estimates the amount of &amp;ldquo;inbreeding&amp;rdquo; or within deme relatedness under the assumption that relatedness between two locations in space can be measured from the average pairwise IBD between those two locations conditional on the physical distance that separates them. Further, we assume that geographic distance is scaled by a migration rate, which is a global parameter among all spatial locations (i.e. the migration rate is assumed to be constant through space). As a result, the model produces a DISC for each spatial location considered (user defined) and an overall migration rate parameter (m). Parameter optimization is achieved with a &amp;ldquo;vanilla&amp;rdquo; gradient descent algorithm. Given that &amp;ldquo;vanilla&amp;rdquo; gradient descent is used, we recommend running numerous models from a wide of array of start parameters to ensure that your final results are the global maximum and not a local maximum (i.e. a false peak).&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Nicholas F Brazeau, &lt;em>in preparation&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Vivax in the DRC</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/drcpv/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/drcpv/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> has long been assumed to be essentially extinct in Sub-Saharan Africa. In this manuscript, we combine techniques from causal inference epidemiolgy, spatial epidemiology, and bioinformatics to describes who is being infected by &lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> in the DRC, where infections are occurring, and where the infections potentially originated. Overall, we suggest that &lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> is persisting in the DRC rather than expanding or thriving. This project was published as Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2021 in Nature Communications&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Mitchell CL, Morgan AP, Deutsch-Feldman M, Watson OJ, Thwai KL, Gelabert P, van Dorp L, Keeler CY, Waltmann A, Emch M, Gartner V, Redelings B, Wray GA, Mwandagalirwa MK, Tshefu AK, Likwela JL, Edwards JK, Verity R, Parr JB, Meshnick SR, Juliano JJ. The epidemiology of Plasmodium vivax among adults in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Nat Commun. 2021 Jul 7;12(1):4169. doi: 10.1038/s41467-021-24216-3. PMID: 34234124; PMCID: PMC8263614.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>`COVIDCurve`: COVID-19 Statistical Modeling</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/covidcurve/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/covidcurve/</guid><description>&lt;p>The purpose of this package is to provide a framework to fit age-specific infection fatality ratios (IFRs) in an epidemic that is using serologic data to estimate prevalence. The model was originally designed in response to the COVID-19 pandemic (hence the name) but is broadly applicable.
Accurate inference of the IFR based on serological data is challenging due to a number of factors that can bias estimates away from the true value, including: (1) the delay between infection and death, (2) the dynamical process of seroconversion and seroreversion, (3) potential differences in age-specific attack rates, and (4) serological test characteristics. These delay-distributions and serologic test characteristics are expected to cause both shifts in when deaths are observed as well as when and how many true infections are observed, which will then affect the IFR.
The model used in &lt;code>COVIDCurve&lt;/code> can be briefly summarized as having two pieces: (1) an infection curve shape that is informed by the shape the of the observed death curve but &amp;ldquo;thrown&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot; backwards in time; (2) a pin or a point on the y-axis that the shape must go through (i.e. a pin to inform the area under the curve, or cumulative infections). This pin is informed by the observed serologic data, accounting for test characteristics (e.g. sensitivity and specificity) as well as the time from infection to seroconversion and seroreversion. Accounting for seroreversion, or the waning of antibodies over time that then produces a false negative test, becomes increasingly important as epidemics progress and/or as daily infections start to contract.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The IFR estimates from this model (&lt;a href="https://github.com/mrc-ide/reestimate_covidIFR_analysis">code repo&lt;/a>) were published as Imperial College London COVID-19 Response Team Report 34&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. The methodological approach for the model was published as a separate manuscript in Communications Medicine &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Verity R, Jenks S, Fu H, Whittaker C, Winskill P, Dorigatti I, Walker PGT, Riley S, Schnekenberg RP, Hoeltgebaum H, Mellan TA, Mishra S, Unwin HJT, Watson OJ, Cucunubá ZM, Baguelin M, Whittles L, Bhatt S, Ghani AC, Ferguson NM, Okell LC.. Report 34 - COVID-19 Infection Fatality Ratio Estimates from Seroprevalence. October 2020. &lt;a href="https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-34-ifr">https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-34-ifr&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Verity R, Jenks S, Fu H, Whittaker C, Winskill P, Dorigatti I, Walker PGT, Riley S, Schnekenberg RP, Hoeltgebaum H, Mellan TA, Mishra S, Unwin HJT, Watson OJ, Cucunubá ZM, Baguelin M, Whittles L, Bhatt S, Ghani AC, Ferguson NM, Okell LC. Estimating the COVID-19 infection fatality ratio accounting for seroreversion using statistical modelling. Commun Med (Lond). 2022 May 19;2:54. doi: 10.1038/s43856-022-00106-7. PMID: 35603270; PMCID: PMC9120146.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>`polySimIBD`: A Simple Malaria Genetic Model</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/polysimibd/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/polysimibd/</guid><description>&lt;p>The goal of polySimIBD is to perform forwards in-time simulation of malaria population genetics. The model uses a discrete-time, discrete-loci structured Wright Fisher approximation to account for (simplified) malaria transmission dynamics and can be parameterized across demes to include a spatial component.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The model was originally used in Verity &amp;amp; Aydemir &amp;amp; Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020 in Nature Communications&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> to assess the bias in our identity by descent calculation.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Verity R, Aydemir O, Brazeau NF, Watson OJ, Hathaway NJ, Mwandagalirwa MK, Marsh PW, Thwai K, Fulton T, Denton M, Morgan AP, Parr JB, Tumwebaze PK, Conrad M, Rosenthal PJ, Ishengoma DS, Ngondi J, Gutman J, Mulenga M, Norris DE, Moss WJ, Mensah BA, Myers-Hansen JL, Ghansah A, Tshefu AK, Ghani AC, Meshnick SR, Bailey JA, Juliano JJ. The impact of antimalarial resistance on the genetic structure of Plasmodium falciparum in the DRC. Nat Commun. 2020 Apr 30;11(1):2107. doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-15779-8. PMID: 32355199; PMCID: PMC7192906.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Antimalarial Resistance in the DRC</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/veritydrc/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/veritydrc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Using a massively parallel amplicon sequencing barcode approach, we used genomic analyses to demonstrate that the DRC appears to be a &amp;ldquo;mixing pot&amp;rdquo; for &lt;em>P. falciparum&lt;/em> infections across Sub-Saharan Africa. In addition, we identified strong signals of selection to antimalarial drugs in the DRC that likely have driven gene flow patterns across the country. Alongside analytic support, I lead the analyses on detecting selection using adapted extended haplotype heterozygosity approaches. In addition, I led the bioinformatic analysis identifying the variants for the aforementioned barcode used in the study. This barcode has been used extensively by our research group, as well as several domestic and international groups (initial publication: Verity/Aydemir/Brazeau et al. 2020, Nat Comms).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tanzania-Zanzibar Transmission</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/tzzb_ibd/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/tzzb_ibd/</guid><description>&lt;p>Significant achievements have been made in Zanzibar in reducing the burden of malaria. However, the region has not been able to achieve malaria elimination. We find that despite existing excellent control efforts, there is ample evidence for gene flow and importation between Zanzibar and mainland Tanzania. This study highlights the challenges for elimination campaigns in addressing sink-source dynamics and the difficulties of blocking genetic corridors, which in theory should lead to a lack of diversity and ecological collapse of the malaria parasite in regions undergoing elimination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project was published as Morgan &amp;amp; Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020 in the Malaria Journal&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Morgan AP, Brazeau NF, Ngasala B, Mhamilawa LE, Denton M, Msellem M, Morris U, Filer DL, Aydemir O, Bailey JA, Parr JB, Mårtensson A, Bjorkman A, Juliano JJ. Falciparum malaria from coastal Tanzania and Zanzibar remains highly connected despite effective control efforts on the archipelago. Malar J. 2020 Jan 28;19(1):47. doi: 10.1186/s12936-020-3137-8. PMID: 31992305; PMCID: PMC6988337.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>