<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>r | Nick Brazeau</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/categories/r/</link><atom:link href="https://nicholasbrazeau.com/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>r</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Nicholas Brazeau</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/img/headers/tree.jpg</url><title>r</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/categories/r/</link></image><item><title>AMR in the Hospital</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/sepidapto/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/sepidapto/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this case study of a patient with &lt;em>Staphylococcus epidermidis&lt;/em> bacteremia receiving prolonged antibiotics that developed Daptomycin resistance, we used whole genome sequencing and bioinformatic analyses to identify a novel mutation. This project demonstrated the utility in using genomic analysis for the identification and survelliance of putative antimicrobial resistant mutations. This project was published as Brazeau &amp;amp; Levinson &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020 in Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Levinson KJ, Schranz A, Moser KA, Hollis I, Iyer P, Chien C, Bowen A, van Duin D, Lachiewicz A, Andermann T, Jones M, Miller M, Juliano JJ, Bartelt LA. Loss of daptomycin susceptibility in clinical Staphylococcus epidermidis infection coincided with variants in WalK. Evol Med Public Health. 2020 Sep 7;2020(1):219-224. doi: 10.1093/emph/eoaa031. PMID: 33214904; PMCID: PMC7658547.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Ethiopia Antimalarial Resistance</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/ephiamr/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/ephiamr/</guid><description>&lt;p>Using samples collected as part of antimalarial drug efficacy studies across Ethiopia over multiple years, we demonstrated that &lt;em>P. falciparum&lt;/em> parasites have evidence of persistence through space and time, despite differing profiles of antimalarial resistance. A main focus of this project was capacity building and increased molecular surveillance capacity at the Ethiopian Public Health Institute and was the first project of a lasting collaboration between the EPHI and UNC. This project was published in the American Journal of Tropical Medicine &amp;amp; Hygeine&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Assefa A, Mohammed H, Seme H, Tsadik AG, Parr JB, Keeler C, Hathaway NJ, Meshnick SR, Bailey JA, Kassa M, Juliano JJ, Woyessa A. Pooled Deep Sequencing of Drug Resistance Loci from Plasmodium falciparum Parasites across Ethiopia. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2019 Nov;101(5):1139-1143. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.19-0142. PMID: 31516103; PMCID: PMC6838589.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>IFR Re-estimation</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/reestimateifr/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/reestimateifr/</guid><description>&lt;p>For a summary of these early re-estimates of the COVID-19 first wave infection fatality ratio estimates accounting for seroreversion, please see the associated &lt;a href="https://www.imperial.ac.uk/news/207273/covid19-deaths-infection-fatality-ratio-says/">press release&lt;/a> that accompanied Report 34&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Verity R, Jenks S, Fu H, Whittaker C, Winskill P, Dorigatti I, Walker PGT, Riley S, Schnekenberg RP, Hoeltgebaum H, Mellan TA, Mishra S, Unwin HJT, Watson OJ, Cucunubá ZM, Baguelin M, Whittles L, Bhatt S, Ghani AC, Ferguson NM, Okell LC.. Report 34 - COVID-19 Infection Fatality Ratio Estimates from Seroprevalence. October 2020. &lt;a href="https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-34-ifr">https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-34-ifr&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Discent</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/discent/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/discent/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a simple package with a single function that runs a simple isolation by distance and identity by descent model for producing deme inbreeding spatial coefficients (DISCs). By theory, genetic relatnedness is strictly limited to measure of identity by descent. For a full mathematical overview of the simple model, please see the supplements from Brazeau et al. 2022 in in preperation&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Briefly, in the early 1970s, Malécot described a relationship between genetic relatedness and physical distance under the premise that pairs that are far apart are less likely to mate: isolation by distance. Capitalizing on this framework by using measures of identity by descent (IBD), we produce a deme inbreeding spatial coefficient (DISC) for point process data in continuous space. Essentially, this measure estimates the amount of &amp;ldquo;inbreeding&amp;rdquo; or within deme relatedness under the assumption that relatedness between two locations in space can be measured from the average pairwise IBD between those two locations conditional on the physical distance that separates them. Further, we assume that geographic distance is scaled by a migration rate, which is a global parameter among all spatial locations (i.e. the migration rate is assumed to be constant through space). As a result, the model produces a DISC for each spatial location considered (user defined) and an overall migration rate parameter (m). Parameter optimization is achieved with a &amp;ldquo;vanilla&amp;rdquo; gradient descent algorithm. Given that &amp;ldquo;vanilla&amp;rdquo; gradient descent is used, we recommend running numerous models from a wide of array of start parameters to ensure that your final results are the global maximum and not a local maximum (i.e. a false peak).&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Nicholas F Brazeau, &lt;em>in preparation&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Vivax in the DRC</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/drcpv/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/drcpv/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> has long been assumed to be essentially extinct in Sub-Saharan Africa. In this manuscript, we combine techniques from causal inference epidemiolgy, spatial epidemiology, and bioinformatics to describes who is being infected by &lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> in the DRC, where infections are occurring, and where the infections potentially originated. Overall, we suggest that &lt;em>P. vivax&lt;/em> is persisting in the DRC rather than expanding or thriving. This project was published as Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2021 in Nature Communications&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Mitchell CL, Morgan AP, Deutsch-Feldman M, Watson OJ, Thwai KL, Gelabert P, van Dorp L, Keeler CY, Waltmann A, Emch M, Gartner V, Redelings B, Wray GA, Mwandagalirwa MK, Tshefu AK, Likwela JL, Edwards JK, Verity R, Parr JB, Meshnick SR, Juliano JJ. The epidemiology of Plasmodium vivax among adults in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Nat Commun. 2021 Jul 7;12(1):4169. doi: 10.1038/s41467-021-24216-3. PMID: 34234124; PMCID: PMC8263614.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>COVIDCurve</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/covidcurve/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/covidcurve/</guid><description>&lt;p>The purpose of this package is to provide a framework to fit age-specific infection fatality ratios (IFRs) in an epidemic that is using serologic data to estimate prevalence. The model was originally designed in response to the COVID-19 pandemic (hence the name) but is broadly applicable.
Accurate inference of the IFR based on serological data is challenging due to a number of factors that can bias estimates away from the true value, including: (1) the delay between infection and death, (2) the dynamical process of seroconversion and seroreversion, (3) potential differences in age-specific attack rates, and (4) serological test characteristics. These delay-distributions and serologic test characteristics are expected to cause both shifts in when deaths are observed as well as when and how many true infections are observed, which will then affect the IFR.
The model used in &lt;code>COVIDCurve&lt;/code> can be briefly summarized as having two pieces: (1) an infection curve shape that is informed by the shape the of the observed death curve but &amp;ldquo;thrown&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot; backwards in time; (2) a pin or a point on the y-axis that the shape must go through (i.e. a pin to inform the area under the curve, or cumulative infections). This pin is informed by the observed serologic data, accounting for test characteristics (e.g. sensitivity and specificity) as well as the time from infection to seroconversion and seroreversion. Accounting for seroreversion, or the waning of antibodies over time that then produces a false negative test, becomes increasingly important as epidemics progress and/or as daily infections start to contract.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The IFR estimates from this model (&lt;a href="https://github.com/mrc-ide/reestimate_covidIFR_analysis">code repo&lt;/a>) were published as Imperial College London COVID-19 Response Team Report 34&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. The methodological approach for the model was published as a separate manuscript in Communications Medicine &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Verity R, Jenks S, Fu H, Whittaker C, Winskill P, Dorigatti I, Walker PGT, Riley S, Schnekenberg RP, Hoeltgebaum H, Mellan TA, Mishra S, Unwin HJT, Watson OJ, Cucunubá ZM, Baguelin M, Whittles L, Bhatt S, Ghani AC, Ferguson NM, Okell LC.. Report 34 - COVID-19 Infection Fatality Ratio Estimates from Seroprevalence. October 2020. &lt;a href="https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-34-ifr">https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-34-ifr&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>Brazeau NF, Verity R, Jenks S, Fu H, Whittaker C, Winskill P, Dorigatti I, Walker PGT, Riley S, Schnekenberg RP, Hoeltgebaum H, Mellan TA, Mishra S, Unwin HJT, Watson OJ, Cucunubá ZM, Baguelin M, Whittles L, Bhatt S, Ghani AC, Ferguson NM, Okell LC. Estimating the COVID-19 infection fatality ratio accounting for seroreversion using statistical modelling. Commun Med (Lond). 2022 May 19;2:54. doi: 10.1038/s43856-022-00106-7. PMID: 35603270; PMCID: PMC9120146.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Antimalarial Resistance in the DRC</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/veritydrc/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/veritydrc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Using a massively parallel amplicon sequencing barcode approach, we used genomic analyses to demonstrate that the DRC appears to be a &amp;ldquo;mixing pot&amp;rdquo; for &lt;em>P. falciparum&lt;/em> infections across Sub-Saharan Africa. In addition, we identified strong signals of selection to antimalarial drugs in the DRC that likely have driven gene flow patterns across the country. Alongside analytic support, I lead the analyses on detecting selection using adapted extended haplotype heterozygosity approaches. In addition, I led the bioinformatic analysis identifying the variants for the aforementioned barcode used in the study. This barcode has been used extensively by our research group, as well as several domestic and international groups (initial publication: Verity/Aydemir/Brazeau et al. 2020, Nat Comms).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>polySimIBD</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/polysimibd/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/polysimibd/</guid><description>&lt;p>The goal of polySimIBD is to perform forwards in-time simulation of malaria population genetics. The model uses a discrete-time, discrete-loci structured Wright Fisher approximation to account for (simplified) malaria transmission dynamics and can be parameterized across demes to include a spatial component.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The model was originally used in Verity &amp;amp; Aydemir &amp;amp; Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020 in Nature Communications&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> to assess the bias in our identity by descent calculation.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Verity R, Aydemir O, Brazeau NF, Watson OJ, Hathaway NJ, Mwandagalirwa MK, Marsh PW, Thwai K, Fulton T, Denton M, Morgan AP, Parr JB, Tumwebaze PK, Conrad M, Rosenthal PJ, Ishengoma DS, Ngondi J, Gutman J, Mulenga M, Norris DE, Moss WJ, Mensah BA, Myers-Hansen JL, Ghansah A, Tshefu AK, Ghani AC, Meshnick SR, Bailey JA, Juliano JJ. The impact of antimalarial resistance on the genetic structure of Plasmodium falciparum in the DRC. Nat Commun. 2020 Apr 30;11(1):2107. doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-15779-8. PMID: 32355199; PMCID: PMC7192906.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Tanzania-Zanzibar Transmission</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/tzzb_ibd/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/tzzb_ibd/</guid><description>&lt;p>Significant achievements have been made in Zanzibar in reducing the burden of malaria. However, the region has not been able to achieve malaria elimination. We find that despite existing excellent control efforts, there is ample evidence for gene flow and importation between Zanzibar and mainland Tanzania. This study highlights the challenges for elimination campaigns in addressing sink-source dynamics and the difficulties of blocking genetic corridors, which in theory should lead to a lack of diversity and ecological collapse of the malaria parasite in regions undergoing elimination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project was published as Morgan &amp;amp; Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020 in the Malaria Journal&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Morgan AP, Brazeau NF, Ngasala B, Mhamilawa LE, Denton M, Msellem M, Morris U, Filer DL, Aydemir O, Bailey JA, Parr JB, Mårtensson A, Bjorkman A, Juliano JJ. Falciparum malaria from coastal Tanzania and Zanzibar remains highly connected despite effective control efforts on the archipelago. Malar J. 2020 Jan 28;19(1):47. doi: 10.1186/s12936-020-3137-8. PMID: 31992305; PMCID: PMC6988337.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Interacting with The Demographic and Health Surveys (DHS) Program data</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/2019/01/29/rdhs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/2019/01/29/rdhs/</guid><description>
&lt;p>This is a copy of &lt;a href="https://ropensci.org/blog/2019/01/29/rdhs/">my article for ROpenSci&lt;/a>
detailing the &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code> package:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There seem to be a lot of ways to write about your R package, and rather than have
to decide on what to focus on I thought I’d write a little bit about everything.
To begin with I thought it best to describe what problem &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code> tries to solve,
why it was developed and how I came to be involved in this project. I then give a
brief overview of what the package can do, before continuing to
describe how writing my first proper package and the rOpenSci
review process was. Lastly I wanted to share a couple of things that I learnt along
the way. These are not very clever or difficult things,
but rather things that were difficult to Google, which now I think about it should probably
be the best metric for a difficult problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;div id="motivation" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>Motivation&lt;/h3>
&lt;div id="what-is-the-dhs-program" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>What is the DHS Program&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://www.dhsprogram.com">Demographic and Health Survey (DHS) Program&lt;/a>
has collected and disseminated population survey data from
over 90 countries for over 30 years. This amounts to over 400
surveys that give representative data on health indicators, which in
many countries provides the key data that mark progress towards targets such as
the &lt;a href="https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/sdgs">Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs)&lt;/a>. In addition,
DHS survey data has been used to inform health policy such as detailing trends in child mortality&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1">&lt;sup>1&lt;/sup>&lt;/a>
and characterising the distribution of malaria control interventions in Africa in order to map the
burden of malaria&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2">&lt;sup>2&lt;/sup>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is all to the say that the DHS provides really useful data. However, although
standard health indicators are routinely published in the survey final reports
that are published by the DHS program, much of the value of the
DHS data is derived from the ability to download and analyse the raw
datasets for subgroup analysis, pooled multi-country analysis, and extended
research studies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This where I got involved, in trying to create a tool that helped enable
researchers to quickly gain access to the raw data sets.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="how-i-got-involved" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>How I got involved&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I am fortunate enough to be a PhD student in a really large department at
Imperial College London, which means that I get the opportunity to be
involved in many projects that are outside the scope of my actual PhD.
The “downside” of that is sometimes you get given “code monkey” jobs as the
bottom rung of the monkey ladder. And so, a few months into my PhD (Nov 2016),
I was given the job of downloading data on malaria test results from
the DHS program that was going to be used by some collaborators.
At the time I was very happy to be involved, however, I was
apprehensive to spend too long on the job as I didn’t know how much time to be
spending on side projects vs my PhD (something I still don’t know with 6 months
to go). This combined with only having a year or so’s experience writing R meant
that the code I wrote to do the job was a bunch of scrappy scripts that required
manually downloading the datasets before parsing them with these R scripts. Dirty
but it got the job done.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some time passed, and another collaborator wanted some different data collated
from the DHS program. At this point, I had 6 more months familiarity with
R and knew a bit more so I started writing it as an R package. However, it was
still messy and it required manually downloading the datasets first, but I was
happy with it and again it wasn’t a major project of mine. This would have been
probably where the project ended if I hadn’t had a conversation (Sept 2017)
in the tea room (prompted solely by the presence of free biscuits) with the
other main author of &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code>, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/eatonjw">Jeff Eaton&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We got chatting, and realised we both had a bunch of scripts for doing bits of
the analysis pipeline. We also realised that we had both had numerous requests
for data sets from the DHS program at which point we thought it would be best
to do something properly. I had also at this point been keen to start using &lt;code>testhat&lt;/code>
within my work as I had been told it would save me time in the future, and up till
that point I hadn’t found a good case to get to grips with it (mainly writing code
on my own, that was never very big and was only used by myself). And so we started
writing &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code>, which was accepted by &lt;code>rOpenSci&lt;/code> and &lt;code>CRAN&lt;/code> in December 2018.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="package-overview" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>Package overview&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Disclaimer: The following section (the &lt;strong>API&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Dataset Downloads&lt;/strong>
headings) is an overiew of the &lt;a href="https://docs.ropensci.org/rdhs/articles/introduction.html">Introduction Vignette&lt;/a>.
If you want a longer introduction to the package then head there, otherwise carry on and
eventually you will get to my ramblings about the package development process.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Most of the functionality of &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code> can be roughly summarised in the 5 main steps
that are involved from wanting to get data on &lt;em>x&lt;/em> to having
a curated data set created from survey data from multiple surveys. These steps
involve:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
&lt;li>Accessing standard survey indicators through the &lt;a href="https://api.dhsprogram.com/">DHS API&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using the API to identifying the surveys and datasets relevant to your particular analysis, i.e.
the ones that ask questions related to your topic of interest.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Downloading survey datasets from the &lt;a href="https://dhsprogram.com/data/available-datasets.cfm">DHS website&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Loading the datasets and associated metadata into R.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Extracting variables and combining datasets for pooled multi-survey analyses.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>We will quickly cover these 5 main steps, with the first 2 showing how &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code> functions
as an API client and the last 3 points showing how &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code> can be used to download
raw data sets from the DHS website. Before we have a look at these, let’s first load &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code>library(rdhs)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="api" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>API&lt;/h3>
&lt;div id="access-standard-indicator-data-via-the-api" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>1. Access standard indicator data via the API&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The DHS program has published an API that gives access to 12
different data sets. Each API endpoint represents one of the 12 data sets
(e.g. &lt;a href="https://api.dhsprogram.com/rest/dhs/tags" class="uri">https://api.dhsprogram.com/rest/dhs/tags&lt;/a>), and can be accessed using the &lt;code>dhs_&amp;lt;&amp;gt;()&lt;/code> functions. For
more information about this see the &lt;a href="https://api.dhsprogram.com/#/index.html">DHS API website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of those functions, &lt;code>dhs_data()&lt;/code>, interacts with the the published
set of standard health indicator data calculated by the DHS. For example, to find out the
trends in antimalarial use in Africa, and see if perhaps antimalarial prescription has
decreased after rapid diagnostic tests were introduced (assumed 2010).&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># Make an api request
resp &amp;lt;- dhs_data(indicatorIds = &amp;quot;ML_FEVT_C_AML&amp;quot;, surveyYearStart = 2010,breakdown = &amp;quot;subnational&amp;quot;)
# filter it to 12 countries for space
countries &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;Angola&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Ghana&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Kenya&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Liberia&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;Madagascar&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Mali&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Malawi&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Nigeria&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;Rwanda&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Sierra Leone&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Senegal&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Tanzania&amp;quot;)
# and plot the results
library(ggplot2)
ggplot(resp[resp$CountryName %in% countries,],
aes(x=SurveyYear,y=Value,colour=CountryName)) +
geom_point() +
geom_smooth(method = &amp;quot;glm&amp;quot;) +
theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 90, vjust = .5)) +
ylab(resp$Indicator[1]) +
facet_wrap(~CountryName,ncol = 6) &lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="featured.jpg" />&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="identify-surveys-relevant-for-further-analysis" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>2. Identify surveys relevant for further analysis&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>You may, however, wish to do more nuanced analysis than the API allows.
The following 4 sections detail a very basic example of how to quickly
identify, download and extract datasets you are interested in.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let’s say we want to get all DHS survey data from the Democratic Republic of
Congo and Tanzania in the last 5 years (since 2013), which covers the use of
rapid diagnostic tests for malaria (“RDT” below). To begin we’ll interact with the
DHS API to identify our datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code>## make a call with no arguments
sc &amp;lt;- dhs_survey_characteristics()
sc[grepl(&amp;quot;Malaria&amp;quot;, sc$SurveyCharacteristicName), ]&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## SurveyCharacteristicID SurveyCharacteristicName
## 57 96 Malaria - DBS
## 58 90 Malaria - Microscopy
## 59 89 Malaria - RDT
## 60 57 Malaria module
## 61 8 Malaria/bednet questions&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>There are 87 different survey characteristics, with one specific survey
characteristic for malaria rapid diagnostic tests (RDT). In this example we will use this to find the surveys
that include this characteristic. (There are other ways to find the
datasets with the API and other options to control how to filter the API, which are
explored &lt;a href="https://docs.ropensci.org/rdhs/articles/introduction.html#identify-surveys-relevant-for-further-analysis">here&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># lets find all the surveys that fit our search criteria
survs &amp;lt;- dhs_surveys(surveyCharacteristicIds = 89,
countryIds = c(&amp;quot;CD&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;TZ&amp;quot;),
surveyType = &amp;quot;DHS&amp;quot;,
surveyYearStart = 2013)
# and lastly use this to find the datasets we will want to download
# and let&amp;#39;s download the flat files (.dat) datasets
datasets &amp;lt;- dhs_datasets(surveyIds = survs$SurveyId,
fileFormat = &amp;quot;flat&amp;quot;,
fileType = &amp;quot;PR&amp;quot;)
str(datasets)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## &amp;#39;data.frame&amp;#39;: 2 obs. of 13 variables:
## $ FileFormat : chr &amp;quot;Flat ASCII data (.dat)&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Flat ASCII data (.dat)&amp;quot;
## $ FileSize : int 6595349 6622102
## $ DatasetType : chr &amp;quot;Survey Datasets&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Survey Datasets&amp;quot;
## $ SurveyNum : int 421 485
## $ SurveyId : chr &amp;quot;CD2013DHS&amp;quot; &amp;quot;TZ2015DHS&amp;quot;
## $ FileType : chr &amp;quot;Household Member Recode&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Household Member Recode&amp;quot;
## $ FileDateLastModified: chr &amp;quot;September, 19 2016 09:58:23&amp;quot; &amp;quot;August, 07 2018 17:36:25&amp;quot;
## $ SurveyYearLabel : chr &amp;quot;2013-14&amp;quot; &amp;quot;2015-16&amp;quot;
## $ SurveyType : chr &amp;quot;DHS&amp;quot; &amp;quot;DHS&amp;quot;
## $ SurveyYear : int 2013 2015
## $ DHS_CountryCode : chr &amp;quot;CD&amp;quot; &amp;quot;TZ&amp;quot;
## $ FileName : chr &amp;quot;CDPR61FL.ZIP&amp;quot; &amp;quot;TZPR7AFL.ZIP&amp;quot;
## $ CountryName : chr &amp;quot;Congo Democratic Republic&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Tanzania&amp;quot;&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>We can now use this to download our datasets for further analysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="dataset-downloads" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>Dataset Downloads&lt;/h3>
&lt;div id="download-survey-datasets" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>3. Download survey datasets&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>To be able to download survey datasets from the DHS website,
we need to set up an account through the DHS website to
enable you to request access to the datasets. Instructions on how to do this can
be found &lt;a href="https://dhsprogram.com/data/Access-Instructions.cfm">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once we have created an account, we set up our credentials using the
function &lt;code>set_rdhs_config()&lt;/code>. See the
&lt;a href="https://docs.ropensci.org/rdhs/articles/introduction.html#download-survey-datasets">Introduction Vignette&lt;/a>
for more clarity about the various options for setting up your config.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code>## set up your credentials
set_rdhs_config(email = &amp;quot;rdhs.tester@gmail.com&amp;quot;,
project = &amp;quot;Testing Malaria Investigations&amp;quot;,
cache_path = &amp;quot;project_one&amp;quot;,
config_path = &amp;quot;~/.rdhs.json&amp;quot;,
data_frame = &amp;quot;data.table::as.data.table&amp;quot;,
global = TRUE)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>We can now download the data sets we identified earlier from the API, using &lt;code>get_datasets&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># download datasets
downloads &amp;lt;- get_datasets(datasets$FileName)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="load-datasets-and-associated-metadata-into-r" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>4. Load datasets and associated metadata into R&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>We can now examine what it is we have actually downloaded, by reading in one of these datasets:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># read in our dataset
cdpr &amp;lt;- readRDS(downloads$CDPR61FL)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The dataset returned here contains all the survey questions within the dataset.&lt;br />
The dataset is by default stored as a &lt;em>labelled&lt;/em> class from the &lt;a href="https://github.com/tidyverse/haven">haven package&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If we want to get the data dictionary for this dataset, we can use the function
&lt;code>get_variable_labels&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># let&amp;#39;s look at the variable_names
head(get_variable_labels(cdpr))&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## variable description
## 1 hhid Case Identification
## 2 hvidx Line number
## 3 hv000 Country code and phase
## 4 hv001 Cluster number
## 5 hv002 Household number
## 6 hv003 Respondent&amp;#39;s line number (answering Household questionnaire)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The default behaviour for the function &lt;code>get_datasets&lt;/code> was
to download the datasets, read them in, and save the resultant &lt;code>data.frame&lt;/code> as a
&lt;code>.rds&lt;/code> object within the cache directory. It also creates the data dictionary and
caches this for you, which allows us to
quickly query for particular &lt;code>variables&lt;/code> or &lt;code>variable_labels&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># rapid diagnostic test search
questions &amp;lt;- search_variable_labels(datasets$FileName, search_terms = &amp;quot;malaria rapid test&amp;quot;)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>Or if we know what variables we want, we can identify which surveys include these:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># and grab the questions from this now utilising the survey variables
questions &amp;lt;- search_variables(datasets$FileName, variables = c(&amp;quot;hv024&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;hml35&amp;quot;))
head(questions)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## variable description dataset_filename
## 1 hv024 Province CDPR61FL
## 2 hml35 Result of malaria rapid test CDPR61FL
## 3 hv024 Region TZPR7AFL
## 4 hml35 Result of malaria rapid test TZPR7AFL
## dataset_path
## 1 /home/oj/GoogleDrive/AcademicWork/Imperial/git/rdhs/paper/project_one/datasets/CDPR61FL.rds
## 2 /home/oj/GoogleDrive/AcademicWork/Imperial/git/rdhs/paper/project_one/datasets/CDPR61FL.rds
## 3 /home/oj/GoogleDrive/AcademicWork/Imperial/git/rdhs/paper/project_one/datasets/TZPR7AFL.rds
## 4 /home/oj/GoogleDrive/AcademicWork/Imperial/git/rdhs/paper/project_one/datasets/TZPR7AFL.rds
## survey_id
## 1 CD2013DHS
## 2 CD2013DHS
## 3 TZ2015DHS
## 4 TZ2015DHS&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>More information about download options and querying the survey questions can be found
&lt;a href="https://docs.ropensci.org/rdhs/articles/introduction.html#load-datasets-and-associated-metadata-into-r-">here&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="extract-variables-and-combine-datasets" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>5. Extract variables and combine datasets&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>To extract our data we pass our questions object to the function &lt;code>extract_dhs&lt;/code>,
which will create a list with each dataset and its extracted data as a &lt;code>data.frame&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># extract the data and add geographic information too
extract &amp;lt;- extract_dhs(questions, add_geo = FALSE)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The resultant extract is a list, with a new element for each different dataset
that you have extracted. We can now combine our two data frames for further analysis using the &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code> package
function &lt;code>rbind_labelled()&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># first let&amp;#39;s bind our first extraction, without the hv024
extract_bound &amp;lt;- rbind_labelled(extract)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## Warning in rbind_labelled(extract): Some variables have non-matching value labels: hv024.
## Inheriting labels from first data frame with labels.&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The thrown warning has shown us that &lt;em>hv024&lt;/em> did not have matching labels between
the two lists, and the labels from the first list have been used.
&lt;em>hv024&lt;/em> stores the regions for these 2 countries, and we probably want to keep all
the labels, which we can do by using the &lt;code>labels&lt;/code> argument:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># lets try concatenating the hv024
better_bound &amp;lt;- rbind_labelled(extract, labels = list(&amp;quot;hv024&amp;quot;=&amp;quot;concatenate&amp;quot;))&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>We could also specify new labels for a variable. For example, imagine the two
datasets encoded their rapid diagnostic test responses differently, with the first one as
&lt;code>c("No","Yes")&lt;/code> and the other as &lt;code>c("Negative","Positive")&lt;/code>. We can choose to
relabel these, e.g. as &lt;code>c("NegativeTest","PositiveTest")&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># lets try concatenating the hv024 and providing new labels
better_bound &amp;lt;- rbind_labelled(
extract,
labels = list(&amp;quot;hv024&amp;quot;=&amp;quot;concatenate&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;hml35&amp;quot;=c(&amp;quot;NegativeTest&amp;quot;=0, &amp;quot;PositiveTest&amp;quot;=1))
)
# and our new label
head(attr(better_bound$hml35,&amp;quot;labels&amp;quot;))&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## NegativeTest PositiveTest
## 0 1&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>For more information about controlling how to extract data from your downloaded
sections, see the &lt;a href="https://docs.ropensci.org/rdhs/articles/introduction.html#extract-variables-and-combining-datasets-for-pooled-multi-survey-analyses-">last section in the introduction vignette&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr />
&lt;p>We now have managed to go from our initial request for data about the use of
rapid diagnostic tests for malaria to a finalised data set that
we can use going forwards for any downstream analysis (and hopefully it didn’t
take that long to do it!). This data set includes survey responses from multiple surveys within one data frame, which in this case includes data from Tanzania and the Democratic Republic of Congo. However, it would be easy to extend our earlier API query to include more countries. For example if we had not limited our search to these 2 countries, the same code as above would have returned data from over 200,000 individuals across 21 countries. Similarly if we wanted to include more survey responses, we could have provided different search terms to &lt;code>search_variables&lt;/code> or &lt;code>search_variable_labels&lt;/code>. By widening our search terms, and including more datasets within the search we can easily create data sets that can be used to answer important global health questions such as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
&lt;li>Which malaria RDTs are performing worse in low malaria prevalence regoions?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What is the link between HIV prevalence and wealth?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How far apart should births occur to minmise childhood mortality?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ramblings-after-my-first-completed-package" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>Ramblings after my first completed package&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Clichéd but the process of actually writing a package, and all that entailed,
was a real highlight. I had made R packages before, but I had never done everything that a
good R package should have (tests, effective continuous integration, full documentation,
a &lt;code>pkgdown&lt;/code> website, contribution and code of conduct guides, and so on). One particular
highlight for me was actually having the opportunity to work
on a code base with someone else in a collaborative way. I work in a large collaborative
group, however, this has not translated as much to working on the same set of code
with someone. As a result I’ve never had to properly learn how to use git outside of
&lt;code>clone&lt;/code>, &lt;code>commit&lt;/code> and &lt;code>push&lt;/code>, nor had I made use of much of the useful aspects of GitHub. So learning
how to correctly use branches in git and realising that helpful comments are actually
helpful (eventually) was really great. With this in mind I wanted to thank &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/eatonjw">Jeff Eaton&lt;/a>
again for taking on this project. He definitely helped drive it over the finish line,
and it was nice to have a glimpse at what working as a developer would look like if
I decide to leave pure academia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There were also a few things that before I started writing &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code>
I knew I would have to figure out but I didn’t have a clue where to start, and for
which repeated googling didn’t eventually help with. Fortunately, I work in the
same department as &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rgfitzjohn">Rich FitzJohn&lt;/a>,
so it was great having someone to point me in the right direction. The following
are three of the things that I genuinely had no idea how to do before, so I thought I’d
share them here (and so I can remind myself in the future):&lt;/p>
&lt;div id="logging-into-a-website-from-r" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>1. Logging into a website from R&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The DHS website has a download manager that you can use to select surveys you want to
download, and it will auto generate a list of URLs in a text file. When I saw this, I thought
this would be great for creating a database of what data sets and the URLs a user’s login details
can give them, which can then be cached so that &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code> knows whether you can download a data set
or not. The only problem is, that to download those data sets you need to be logged in, and you
also need to be logged in to get to the download manager. For me, I didn’t know how to translate
being “logged in” into R code, or even what that looked like. But turns out it wasn’t too bad
after being shown by Rich where to start looking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To know where to look I opened up Chrome and went to developer tools. From there I
opened up the &lt;strong>Network Tab&lt;/strong>, which then records the information being sent to the
URL. So to know what information is required to login I simply logged in as normal,
and then inspected what appeared in the network tab’s &lt;strong>Headers Tab&lt;/strong>. This then
showed me what the needed &lt;strong>Request URL&lt;/strong> was, and what information was being
submitted in the &lt;strong>Form Data&lt;/strong> at the bottom of this tab.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="login_form_data.png" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could then use this information to &lt;em>log in&lt;/em> from with R using an &lt;code>httr::POST&lt;/code>
request:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># authentication page
terms &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;https://dhsprogram.com/data/dataset_admin/login_main.cfm&amp;quot;
# create a temporary file
tf &amp;lt;- tempfile(fileext = &amp;quot;.txt&amp;quot;)
# set the username and password
values &amp;lt;- list(
UserName = your_email,
UserPass = your_password,
Submitted = 1,
UserType = 2
)
# log in.
message(&amp;quot;Logging into DHS website...&amp;quot;)
z &amp;lt;- httr::POST(terms, body = values) %&amp;gt;% handle_api_response(to_json = FALSE)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>To me, this seemed really cool, and then meant I could do the same style of
steps to get to the Download Manager webpage and then tick all the check boxes
in the page to generate the URL with all the download links in.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="caching-api-results-from-a-changing-api" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>2. Caching API results from a changing API&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>We wanted to be able to cache a user’s API request for them locally when designing
&lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code>. We felt this was important as it would reduce the burden on the API itself,
as well as enable researchers who were without internet (e.g. currently working in
the field), the ability to still access previous API requests. However, designing
something neat that would be easy to respond to changes in the API version would
I thought be outside my skill set.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Again, enter Rich and this time with his package &lt;a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/storr/index.html">&lt;code>storr&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.
This was a lifesaver, and created an easy infrastructure for storing API responses
in a key-value store. I could then use the specific API URL as the key and the
response as the value. Initially I thought I would have to keep saving the response
with explicit names (e.g. the URL), but &lt;code>storr&lt;/code> handles all this for you, and also
then helps get around having too long file names if your API request is very long for example.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To respond to changes in the API, my solution was perhaps not the neatest, but I
simply kept a record of the date you last made an API request and compared it to
the API’s &lt;a href="https://api.dhsprogram.com/#/api-dataupdates.cfm">data updates endpoint&lt;/a>.
If I could see any recent changes, I then could clear all the API requests cached.
This would made a lot simpler using the &lt;code>namespaces&lt;/code> options in &lt;code>storr&lt;/code>, which meant
that I was able to keep all API cached data in one place, which could then be
easily deleted on mass.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="tests-travis-authentication" class="section level4">
&lt;h4>3. Tests, Travis &amp;amp; Authentication&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The last thing caused me the most amount of headaches. How do I write tests that
require authentication and can use &lt;code>travis&lt;/code> for continuous integration. Initially,
I made a dummy account with the DHS website for this, but realised that sharing
the credentials of an account with access to just dummy data sets would not enable
me to test the weird edge cases that started popping up related to certain data
sets. The first solution that I used for a few months was to set up environment
variables within &lt;code>travis&lt;/code> itself, which could then be used to create a valid
set of credentials.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="travis_env_vars.png" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This worked, however, it meant that I would have to write a lot of the &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code>
functionality to use environment variables that were the user’s email and password,
which felt wrong and quite clunky. All I wanted was to pass to Travis a valid
set of login credentials that would then be used within the tests, much in the same
way that a user would. To do this I had to learn a bit more about what the &lt;code>.travis.yml&lt;/code>
document could actually be used for, because to begin with I had only been using it
to specify the software language.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Again, Rich pointed me to using &lt;code>sodium&lt;/code> to create an encrypted version of a valid
login credentials:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># read in a key from a local file
key &amp;lt;- sodium::hash(charToRaw(readLines(&amp;quot;scripts/key.txt&amp;quot;)))
# create a tat with all the necessary login credentials
zip(&amp;quot;rdhs.json.tar&amp;quot;,files=c(&amp;quot;rdhs.json&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;tests/testthat/rdhs.json&amp;quot;))
# read this tar in as binary data
dat &amp;lt;- readBin(&amp;quot;rdhs.json.tar&amp;quot;,raw(),file.size(&amp;quot;rdhs.json.tar&amp;quot;))
# encrypt the data using sodium and our key before saving it
enc &amp;lt;- sodium::data_encrypt(msg = dat,key = key)
saveRDS(enc,&amp;quot;rdhs.json.tar.enc&amp;quot;)&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>This encrypted copy could be included in the GitHub repository, and I could
set up the key as a Travis environment variable to decrypt it. This decryption
step could then be written within my &lt;code>.travis.yml&lt;/code> file, and would mean that all
my tests had access to my login credentials in a secure way.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr />
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="options-to-contribute" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>Options to Contribute&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>There are a few things that would be great to add in the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
&lt;li>&lt;p>Adding a suite of tools for doing spatial mapping. A lot of the
time, people want to know what the prevalence of x is either at a fine spatial scale,
or grouped at administrative/county/state levels. &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code> helps provide the tools to
get geolocated measures of x, and I think it would be a great next step to add
a suite of mapping tools. It would be great if they could be used to either create a mesh
through these points (probably using &lt;code>INLA&lt;/code>), or calculate survey weighted means at requested
spatial scales or match them to a provided &lt;code>SpatialPolygons&lt;/code> object. Related to this is
it would be good to also link in the &lt;a href="https://spatialdata.dhsprogram.com/home/">Spatial Data Repository&lt;/a>
from the DHS, so that users can easily download shape files for their analyses (&lt;a href="https://github.com/ropensci/rdhs/issues/71">issue #71&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;p>Not related to any specific issues, but it would be good to have a clearer set of
downstream analysis pipelines. One example is a package in development by Jeff Eaton
called &lt;a href="https://github.com/mrc-ide/demogsurv">&lt;code>demogsurv&lt;/code>&lt;/a>, which is used to calculate
common demographic indicators from household survey data, including child mortality,
adult mortality, and fertility. This is just one example, but over time there will
be a number of bespoke analysis tools down the line, and so it would be nice to begin
a collection/grouping of these tools (possibly as a wiki or similar).&lt;/p>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;p>It would be nice to have a way to manually add sources of survey data. At the
moment the pipeline for downloading raw data sets used the DHS API a lot, however, what
if you had some survey data (either locally or shared at a URL) that you wanted to bring
into your analysis pipeline. Something similar to this is done for the &lt;code>model_datasets&lt;/code>
within &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code>, which is a set of dummy data sets that the DHS hosts online but
are not included in their API.&lt;/p>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="acknowledgements-and-final-thoughts" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>Acknowledgements and Final Thoughts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Firstly, I want to thank &lt;a href="https://github.com/annakrystalli">Anna Krystalli&lt;/a> for handling
the review, and for being incredibly patient throughout, especially at the end as we
were fixing the last authentication bug. Also many thanks to &lt;a href="https://github.com/LucyMcGowan">Lucy McGowan&lt;/a>
and &lt;a href="https://github.com/dosgillespie">Duncan Gillespie&lt;/a> for taking the time to
review the package and for their input, which led to lots of improvements (and also
linking the &lt;code>add_line&lt;/code> function from &lt;code>httr&lt;/code> was seriously helpful, and I’ve used
that function in lots of other my other work now). I also wanted to more broadly thank
the review process as a whole. Having the option to discuss the package and needed
solutions with the reviewers within a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ropensci/software-review/issues/238">GitHub issues system&lt;/a> is fantastic. It made the process
personal and was substantially improved over review processes I have had at academic journals.
Lastly, another big thank you &lt;a href="https://github.com/jeffeaton">Jeff Eaton&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/richfitz">Rich FitzJohn&lt;/a>, and also to the infectious
disease epidemiology department at Imperial for providing a lot of really helpful
ginuea pig testing of the numerous iterations of &lt;code>rdhs&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
&lt;hr />
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn1">&lt;p>Silva, Romesh. 2012. “Child Mortality Estimation: Consistency of Under-Five Mortality Rate Estimates Using Full Birth Histories and Summary Birth Histories.” PLoS Medicine 9: e1001296. &lt;a href="doi:%5B10.1371/journal.pmed.1001296" class="uri">doi:[10.1371/journal.pmed.1001296&lt;/a>](&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001296" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1001296&lt;/a>).&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back">↩︎&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn2">&lt;p>Bhatt, S, D J Weiss, E Cameron, D Bisanzio, B Mappin, U Dalrymple, K E Battle, et al. 2015. “The effect of malaria control on Plasmodium falciparum in Africa between 2000 and 2015.”Nature 526: 207–11. &lt;a href="doi:%5B10.1038/nature15535" class="uri">doi:[10.1038/nature15535&lt;/a>](&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature15535" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1038/nature15535&lt;/a>).&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back">↩︎&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>ASTMH 2016 pfhrp2/3 modelling</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/asthm-2016-pfhrp2-3/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 18:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/asthm-2016-pfhrp2-3/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Talk at ASTMH 2016 on pfhrp2/3 deletions. The talk was early discussion of findings now published at
eLife&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1">&lt;sup>1&lt;/sup>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document">
&lt;hr />
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn1">&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://elifesciences.org/articles/25008" class="uri">https://elifesciences.org/articles/25008&lt;/a>&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back">↩︎&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>