<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>active | Nick Brazeau</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/tags/active/</link><atom:link href="https://nicholasbrazeau.com/tags/active/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>active</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Nicholas Brazeau</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 08:00:20 -0700</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/img/headers/tree.jpg</url><title>active</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/tags/active/</link></image><item><title>Discent</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/discent/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/discent/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a simple package with a single function that runs a simple isolation by distance and identity by descent model for producing deme inbreeding spatial coefficients (DISCs). By theory, genetic relatnedness is strictly limited to measure of identity by descent. For a full mathematical overview of the simple model, please see the supplements from Brazeau et al. 2022 in in preperation&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Briefly, in the early 1970s, Malécot described a relationship between genetic relatedness and physical distance under the premise that pairs that are far apart are less likely to mate: isolation by distance. Capitalizing on this framework by using measures of identity by descent (IBD), we produce a deme inbreeding spatial coefficient (DISC) for point process data in continuous space. Essentially, this measure estimates the amount of &amp;ldquo;inbreeding&amp;rdquo; or within deme relatedness under the assumption that relatedness between two locations in space can be measured from the average pairwise IBD between those two locations conditional on the physical distance that separates them. Further, we assume that geographic distance is scaled by a migration rate, which is a global parameter among all spatial locations (i.e. the migration rate is assumed to be constant through space). As a result, the model produces a DISC for each spatial location considered (user defined) and an overall migration rate parameter (m). Parameter optimization is achieved with a &amp;ldquo;vanilla&amp;rdquo; gradient descent algorithm. Given that &amp;ldquo;vanilla&amp;rdquo; gradient descent is used, we recommend running numerous models from a wide of array of start parameters to ensure that your final results are the global maximum and not a local maximum (i.e. a false peak).&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Nicholas F Brazeau, &lt;em>in preparation&lt;/em>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>polySimIBD</title><link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/polysimibd/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 08:00:20 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/project/polysimibd/</guid><description>&lt;p>The goal of polySimIBD is to perform forwards in-time simulation of malaria population genetics. The model uses a discrete-time, discrete-loci structured Wright Fisher approximation to account for (simplified) malaria transmission dynamics and can be parameterized across demes to include a spatial component.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The model was originally used in Verity &amp;amp; Aydemir &amp;amp; Brazeau &lt;em>et al.&lt;/em> 2020 in Nature Communications&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> to assess the bias in our identity by descent calculation.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Verity R, Aydemir O, Brazeau NF, Watson OJ, Hathaway NJ, Mwandagalirwa MK, Marsh PW, Thwai K, Fulton T, Denton M, Morgan AP, Parr JB, Tumwebaze PK, Conrad M, Rosenthal PJ, Ishengoma DS, Ngondi J, Gutman J, Mulenga M, Norris DE, Moss WJ, Mensah BA, Myers-Hansen JL, Ghansah A, Tshefu AK, Ghani AC, Meshnick SR, Bailey JA, Juliano JJ. The impact of antimalarial resistance on the genetic structure of Plasmodium falciparum in the DRC. Nat Commun. 2020 Apr 30;11(1):2107. doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-15779-8. PMID: 32355199; PMCID: PMC7192906.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>