<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent Talks and Workshops | Nick Brazeau</title>
    <link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Recent Talks and Workshops</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2025 Nicholas Brazeau</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/img/headers/tree.jpg</url>
      <title>Recent Talks and Workshops</title>
      <link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 Infection Fatality Ratio: Where we started, Where we were, Where we are</title>
      <link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/ighid-covid-19-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/ighid-covid-19-talk/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Talk at the UNC Institute of Global Health and Infectious Disease monthly conference. The talk was early discussion of statistical modeling and the the evolution of the COVID-19 IFR during the first wave of the pandemic. Our statistical model is now published at Communications Medicine&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes footnotes-end-of-document&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brazeau NF, Verity R, Jenks S, Fu H, Whittaker C, Winskill P, Dorigatti I, Walker PGT, Riley S, Schnekenberg RP, Hoeltgebaum H, Mellan TA, Mishra S, Unwin HJT, Watson OJ, Cucunubá ZM, Baguelin M, Whittles L, Bhatt S, Ghani AC, Ferguson NM, Okell LC. Estimating the COVID-19 infection fatality ratio accounting for seroreversion using statistical modelling. Commun Med (Lond). 2022 May 19;2:54. doi: 10.1038/s43856-022-00106-7. PMID: 35603270; PMCID: PMC9120146.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Patterns of Falciparum Malaria Genetic Relatedness Driven by Human Movement in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title>
      <link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 08:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Remote presentation at the annual American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene conference. Presented early work on the Deme Inbreeding Spatial Coefficient framework and the &lt;code&gt;DISCent&lt;/code&gt; R-package. This project is currently in preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Epidemiology of Asymptomatic P. vivax Among Adults in the Democratic Republic of the Congoo</title>
      <link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 08:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Presentation of the first aim of my PhD dissertation, which focused on the epidemiology of &lt;em&gt;P. vivax&lt;/em&gt; in the Democratic Republic of the Congo, at the annual American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene conference. This work is now published in Nature Communications&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes footnotes-end-of-document&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brazeau NF, Mitchell CL, Morgan AP, Deutsch-Feldman M, Watson OJ, Thwai KL, Gelabert P, van Dorp L, Keeler CY, Waltmann A, Emch M, Gartner V, Redelings B, Wray GA, Mwandagalirwa MK, Tshefu AK, Likwela JL, Edwards JK, Verity R, Parr JB, Meshnick SR, Juliano JJ. The epidemiology of Plasmodium vivax among adults in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Nat Commun. 2021 Jul 7;12(1):4169. doi: 10.1038/s41467-021-24216-3. PMID: 34234124; PMCID: PMC8263614.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>polyIBD: Inferring Identity by Descent in Complex, Polyclonal Infections</title>
      <link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 08:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/discent-astmh/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Presentation at the annual Genomic Epidemiology of Malaria conference presenting early work on &lt;code&gt;polyIBD&lt;/code&gt; a hidden Markov model for inferring identity by descent in polyclonal infections using a Bayesian framework. This project is currently in preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Whole Genome Analysis of Polyclonal Plasmodium vivax Relapses in Cambodia</title>
      <link>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/pvrelapse-astmh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 08:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicholasbrazeau.com/talk/pvrelapse-astmh/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Oral presentation at the annual American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene conference analyzing the genomics of &lt;em&gt;P. vivax&lt;/em&gt; relapses from Cambodia.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
